For years now, Tether's USDT has been
the default crypto dollar. If you've
traded crypto on an exchange or moved
money across borders at light speed,
then you've probably used it. But
there's always been one uncomfortable
aspect to USDT, compliance, especially
in the biggest arena of all, the United
States. So now Tether has made a bold
move. It's launched a separate US
focused stable coin, US80, built for
America's new stablecoin rule book.
That's a shot fired in the stable coin
wars. Tether doesn't just want to
dominate offshore, it also wants a legit
onshore product, too. Right where Circle
and USDC have been strongest. And at the
same time, Tether is sending a totally
different message to the market with
gold. not just their tokenized gold, but
a real horde of precious metal on such a
scale that Tether is now being treated
as a serious player in the $34 trillion
gold market. So, what is USAT? Why build
it alongside USDT? What's the endgame
with all that gold? And how does Tether
plan to remain the king of stable coins?
We dive into all of that and more in
today's video. My name is Guy and you're
watching the Coin Bureau.
First up though, I must make one thing
clear. I'm not a financial adviser and
nothing in this video should be
considered financial advice. This is
just our take on the big moves Tether is
making to retain its crown. And if you
like content like this, then show us by
hitting that like button and let's get
started. All right, let's begin with
Tether's new stable coin UST. The main
difference from Tether's USDT is pretty
straightforward. UST isn't just USDT
branded for the American market. It's a
separate stable coin with a US native
setup created because the US has
established a federal rule book for
stable coins and that rulebook must be
complied with. Tether's CEO Paulo
Arduino announced the launch of USAT
just a couple of weeks ago. Former White
House official Bo Hines leads the
project as CEO of Tether USAT, while
Anchorage Digital Bank will operate as
the issuer. Notably, Tether has said
that USDT will keep operating as a
foreign stable coin, while the new US
product is built to meet regulations
laid out in the Genius Act. In Tether's
official communications regarding USAT,
it outlines all the disclaimers US
regulators want to hear. USAT is not
legal tender. It's not issued or
guaranteed by the US government and it's
not protected by FDIC or SIPC insurance.
That might sound like straightforward
legal stuff, but it isn't. It's the
whole strategy. That's because the
Genius Act sets a baseline for what a
legal stable coin means in the US. The
law states that stable coins must be
backed onetoone with liquid assets like
US dollars or short-term treasuries.
Also, issuers have to publish monthly
public disclosures about reserve
composition. It also highlights strict
marketing rules, no implying your
governmentbacked, insured or legal
tender. And that's why the issuer of the
stable coin is an important factor. When
a stable coin is issued through a
federally supervised bank such as
Anchorage, it changes everything. The
focus is no longer on whether the peg
holds because there's a strict set of
examinations, oversight, and operating
standards inside a system built to
punish financial funny business.
Anchorage issues USAT directly from its
federally regulated bank under the
oversight of the office of the
controller of the currency. It's
essentially Anchorage broadcasting that
USAT is being produced inside the
American banking perimeter with bank
grade compliance, risk management, and
reserve transparency presented as core
features. So where does that leave USDT?
Well, USDT remains the global
heavyweight. It's the token that is
already everywhere in crypto, used by
traders, exchanges, and people who just
want digital dollars that move fast and
freely. But Tether knows the US is
changing the rules of engagement and the
US is of course a major market for
crypto. So instead of trying to force
USDT to operate in some kind of gray
area, Tether is creating a dedicated US
product that starts with compliance and
works backwards. That's the realization
that Tether appears to have had. So USAT
is Tether acknowledging that being the
biggest isn't the same as being welcome
in the biggest market. And with that,
you can see what Tether is really trying
to do. Keep USDT dominant globally while
making sure it can't be boxed out of US
institutional demand as stable coins get
pulled deeper into regulated finance.
So, USAT is an effort from Tether to not
only retain its title as the leading
stable coin issuer, but also go after
more market share. But how firm is
Tether's lead? Is it now set to eat its
competitors? Well, according to Coin
Gecko data, USDT sits at a $185 billion
market cap, while the newly minted US
has a market cap of $20 million.
Granted, it's in its infancy. In any
case, Tether dominates the stable coin
market with about 60% market share,
while Circle's USDC, the next largest
competitor, sits at only 23%. But if you
want to understand the stable coin war,
it makes more sense to see what the
trajectory has been like recently. Why?
Well, because crypto has been trending
down for months and now even the total
stable coin market cap is falling. When
times are tough and BTC is dragging all
manner of market metrics down with it,
you get insight into which crypto assets
have more resilience. Since mid January
2026, the overall stable coin market cap
began to decline from its peak of $311
billion. And who was leading the way?
Circles USDC. But let's put numbers on
this to better illustrate the point. At
the time of making this video, in the
early days of February 2026, USDT sits
at a market cap of about $185 billion.
since mid January when the total stable
coin market cap began falling. That's
only down around 0.9%
from its all-time high. Meanwhile, USDC
now sits at just under 71 billion. Since
mid January, that's down about 6.5%.
So, both are feeling the pressure as
crypto goes further risk off. But USDC
has been shrinking a lot faster. And
that gap is where the real fight is
happening because USDC and USDT have
always had different selling points.
Circle's main selling point has been
compliance. A stable coin that always
plays by the rules and is built for the
regulated world. And that's important
for people or entities moving size like
banks, payments giants, and other
institutions with strict compliance.
Case in point, in December last year,
Visa announced it was expanding stable
coin settlement for US banks using USDC.
And that form of integration is
precisely where circle plans to thrive.
It may not be the most exciting headline
for crypton natives, but it's the sort
of thing that creates an avenue for
major stable coin adoption. Tether's
main edge, on the other hand, has
historically been distribution. USDT
started the stable coin model we know
today. It's the first stable coin most
people in crypto started their journey
with and it's widely used across all
manner of exchanges and even across
borders. Tether's brand is the default
for many crypto natives and the firm has
only built on that reputation over the
years. Now, the problem for Circle is
that compliance has been a moat mainly
because Tether didn't have a US product
that could credibly play that game. But
that's what changed at the end of
January when Tether and Anchorage
Digital announced the US focused UST.
USAT is the first credible domestic
competitor for institutional dollars
that could genuinely threaten Circle's
positioning around USDC. So shots very
much fired because if Tether can keep
its global dominance with USDT and also
offer a USfriendly option with US80,
then Circle's main differentiator begins
to look less exclusive. But having said
that, Circle excels in a metric that's
hard to ignore, user activity. According
to data from Artemis Analytics, stable
coin transactions hit $33 trillion in
2025 and USDC accounted for $18.3
trillion of that versus 13.3 trillion
for USDT. So even while USDT is much
larger by supply, USDC has been doing
more movement. That tells you the
crucial difference. Supply dominance and
usage dominance aren't the same thing.
Tether's brand can be the default
digital dollar people hold and quote
against, while USDC can be the one
that's used disproportionately in
settlement and highfrequency onchain
activity. In a downturn, both can
shrink, but they shrink for different
reasons and to different degrees. And by
the way, if you want to stay informed on
the battle between Tether and Circle as
it rages on, then you should sign up for
the weekly Coinbureau newsletter. It's
absolutely free and you can sign up
using the link in the description. And
while you're at it, why not check out
the exclusive deals we've secured for
viewers of this channel. These include
huge signup bonuses and trading fee
discounts on crypto's leading exchanges,
great deals on hardware wallets, and
much more. All that is accessible via
this QR code right here. So, take a
look. Now, Tether's strategic stable
coin moves are one thing, but if we want
to know what Tether thinks the future
looks like, we need to look beyond the
stable coins themselves and look closer
at Tether's reserves. What sticks out?
Gold and lots of it. In the latest
assurance report covering the end of
2025, Tether's issuer entity says it had
$192 billion in reserves backing its
fiat peg tokens with assets exceeding
liabilities by about $6.3 billion. In
the breakup of what's backing USDT,
precious metals comes in at $17.45
billion. And what's that referring to
exactly? Physical gold bars owned by
Tether International. Now, that whopping
hoorde of gold is changing the optics
around Tether, the organization. Sure,
the majority is still classic stable
coin stuff like shortdated treasury
bills and reverse repo, but once you're
holding gold in the tens of billions,
you're carving out a prominent place for
yourself in the $34 trillion gold
market. And that's exactly how Tether
wants to be seen. Mainstream media has
been reporting that Tether has become a
serious presence in the gold market.
Based on that latest attestation,
Bloomberg estimated Tether had a pile of
around 140 tons stored in Switzerland.
That's big enough such that it's
described as the largest known stash of
bullion outside of banks and nation
states. Tether CEO Paulo Arduino offered
some comment to Reuters that align with
that estimate. He told reporters that
Tether already had about 130 metric tons
of physical gold and that they're buying
roughly two tons a week. Arduino said
the firm wants gold to represent
something like 10 to 15% of the firm's
investment portfolio over time. So just
what the heck is Tether up to here?
Well, for one, the gold can be viewed as
a macro hedge. Gold's been on a tear
even considering the recent sell-off.
And if you're throwing off huge profits
from rate driven income, converting some
of that into a hard asset could make
sense. But the deeper play is
reputational. Tether is trying to
graduate from a crypto issuer that
prints USDT to a collateral manager that
can run reserves across industries and
across cycles. There's also the pure
business side of things with Tether's
tokenized gold. Now, to be clear, the
gold backing Tether's tokenized gold
token X aut is separate from the gold on
Tether's balance sheet regarding USDT.
But anyway, the tokenized gold market
sits at over $6 billion, growing 4x
since the end of 2024. Tether wants to
dominate that market as it does US
dollar stable coins. But this is where
the gold story stops being universally
flattering because backing tokenized
gold with actual gold is
straightforward. But Tether using gold
as partial backing for USDT is another
thing entirely and it's drawing some
scrutiny from the market. In November,
S&P Global downgraded its stability
assessment of USDT to five, the lowest
score on its scale. They cited Tether's
increased exposure to higher risk assets
like BTC and gold alongside secured
loans, corporate bonds, and what S&P
called persistent gaps in disclosure
around custodians and counterparties.
Now, as anyone who's studied the 2008
global financial crisis can tell you,
ratings agencies don't always get it
right. Far from it. Nevertheless, S&P
Global's perception of Tether still
captures the institutional mindset.
Stable coins are supposed to be boring.
The more complicated the backing gets,
the more you're asking the market to
trust your judgment under pressure. In
that context, Tether's issuance of a US
compliant USAT is no surprise. It's a
clear move to capture more institutional
demand for stable coins. But in any
case, Tether reportedly finds itself
holding 140 plus tons of gold, and that
will play a key role in the company's
future plans. But what do those plans
actually look like? What is Tether's
strategy going forward? Well, for
starters, with that 140 tons of gold,
Tether isn't just collecting shiny
rocks. It's starting to treat bullion
like a business. In late 2025, Tether
planned a dramatic expansion in lending
to commodities traders after extending
roughly $1.5 billion worth of credit.
That's notable because commodity trading
is basically built on credit and
collateral. If you have a monster
balance sheet and a growing pile of
precious metals, you can do more than
just sit there hoping the price goes up.
Tether plans to keep pushing profits
into gold while also starting to compete
with banks in trading the metal,
recruiting two senior gold traders from
HSBC late last year. That's a pretty
clear signal. They're not only thinking
about reserves, they're thinking about
market making and inventory. Tether has
also held talks to invest across the
gold supply chain from mining and
refining to royalty businesses while
also expanding into commodity trade
finance. But let's bring things back to
stable coins because the gold strategy,
as big as it is, sits inside something
bigger. Tether's whole game is
distribution, jurisdictional
positioning, and partnerships with a
side order of diversification. In
January 2025, Tether relocated to El
Salvador after securing a digital asset
service provider license there. And
Paulo Arduino said it would be the
company's first physical headquarters.
That choice is about anchoring the
company in a place that welcomes it
while the rest of the world's
jurisdictions finalize exactly how hard
they want to squeeze stable coins. USAT
has been a clear play. With that in
mind, the US has largely formalized its
view on stable coins and it's a key
market for obvious reasons. And Tether
needs to win in that region because in
other regions, the squeeze has been
real. In Europe, Micro regulations have
pushed exchanges into cutting off stable
coins they can't comfortably support.
Binance has delisted non-compliant
stable coins for EA users, including
USDT. And Asia isn't exactly anything
goes either. Hong Kong's regulator has
been moving slowly, but expects to issue
its first batch of stable coin issuer
licenses in March 2026, and only a very
small number at first. Japan, meanwhile,
already directs issuance through
regulated financial institutions, while
Korea is still building a one stable
coin framework designed to keep issuers
under strict oversight. But beyond
stable coins and gold, Tether is
actually diversifying further. It's
among a long list of firms investing in
Bitcoin mining operations powered by
renewables. The company has also put
money into things as far apart as a $775
million stake in video platform Rumble
and is in talks about a potential 1
billion euro investment into German
robotics firm NORA. So, Tether is
complementing its massive moves in
stable coins and gold with a whole slew
of other major ventures. When a stable
coin issuer is trading gold, financing
commodities, buying energy, and building
a huge investment portfolio, well, the
label of crypto company begins to sound
a little wide of the mark. And given how
broad Tether's activities have become,
it's increasingly difficult to pin down
what kind of company it really is. And
that sets up one of the main criticisms
that's emerged amid its latest push with
USAT.
Can one brand credibly sell two
completely different versions of digital
dollars without the trust issues
bleeding across all while it becomes a
gold behemoth and a venture firm? USAT
changes Tether's business both
explicitly and implicitly. Tether isn't
just promising that everything is fine
anymore. It's explicitly stepping closer
to the world of institutional due
diligence and disclosure expectations
that don't really care about crypto's
old norms. However, now that we have a
US-friendly Tether stable coin, the
brand is implicitly admitting the other
product USDT isn't built for the same
standards. Now, some users won't care.
They just want a stable token that's
widely accepted. But others might wonder
if Tether can do a regulated product for
the US, why should markets tolerate
opacity and reserve complexity in the
offshore giant? And from that
perspective, Tether's hoorde of gold
adds more complexity to this identity
problem. Tether ended 2025 with gold
holdings above $17 billion alongside net
profits topping $10 billion. That's
clearly a company that wants to be seen
as a serious collateral manager, not
just a token issuer. But in that,
they're also handing critics a clear
target. Stable coin backing is supposed
to be boring and liquid, especially
under stress. And as we just saw with
the 30th of January metals wipeout, any
gold backing of USDT becomes more
questionable. Gold dropped over 20%
across just 3 days. And that's not to
mention the moves BTC is capable of
considering it's another alternative
asset backing USDT. So, can Tether pull
off being the best of both worlds
without tripping over itself? Well,
quite possibly if UST stays truly
ringing fenced and institutions treat it
like a separate product with separate
rules. But if the market views Tether as
one unified reputation, then things
could get messy. A controversy around
USDT could contaminate USAT by
association and the scrutiny that comes
with USAT could raise uncomfortable
questions that USDT has historically
been able to sidestep. But for now,
Tether is king and there's no sign of
anyone else taking that crown anytime
soon. Well, that's our outlook on Tether
and its major moves in stable coins and
beyond. But what do you think? Is Tether
destined to remain king or is it trying
to do too much too fast? Let us know
your thoughts down in the comments. And
if you want to find out why stable coins
are at the center of crypto regulation
controversy, you can watch our video on
that right over here. That's all from me
for today, though. As always, thank you
for watching and I'll see you in the
next one. This is Guy signing off.